Hello today's דף daf, *Daf* is עין טית *Ayin Tet*. 8? Okay
get out your pens.
Alright
we are in the middle of עין חית עמוד בית *Ayin Chet
Amud Bet* and it's וכן לעניין קידושין *V'chein L'Inyan Kiddushin*. We had
this whole idea that a throw a גט get *get* near if
it's in רשות הרבים reshus harabbim *Reshus Harabbim* falls near her she's
מגורשת megureshet, *megoreshet* near him she's not. There's a debate what that
meant near her. One opinion was within the ארבע אמות arba amos,
*arba amot* which is the classic way of קנין Kinyan *kinyan* that
חז"ל *Chazal* were מתקן קניינים kinyanim. *metaken kinyanim*. How a rabbinic קנין
kinyan *kinyan* works for a דאורייתא *D'oraisa* we won't get into right
now but anyway that's a קנין ארבע אמות arba amos, *kinyan arba
amot* at least fitting within the classic definition of קנין *kinyan*. And
then you had the position of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan*
which is it's not ארבע אמות arba amos, *arba amot*. It's as
long as she's in a position where she can guard it and
protect it and he can't that's considered to be under her control.
And nobody of course would say such a thing like that for
a קנין *kinyan* of a normal object. You want me to I
want you to buy your basketball I say throw your basketball here
if it doesn't fall within ארבע אמות arba amos. *arba amot* if
it's just in a place where I can protect it that's not
a קנין *kinyan*. So again רבי Rabbi יוחנן'ס *Rabbi Yochanan's* read of
the משנה Mishna *Mishnah* points once again to the idea that the
act of giving a גט get. *get* does not have to be
the same type of an act as what's required to take possession
of an object of a קנין *kinyan*. It could be a נתינה
*netina* without a קנין *kinyan* and therefore even if it's very distant
from the person if they're in a position to protect it that's
how רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan* read the משנה Mishna? *Mishnah*.
But also we did end with the idea of the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* sort of saying well whatever the משנה Mishna, *Mishnah* means in
practice you need to get to actually come straight into her hand
or as תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* says either in her yard or in
her hand. We're not going to use any of this in practice.
So that was actually an interesting pushback and a significant חומרא *chumra*
by גיטין Gittin. *Gittin* because you turn the woman into a ספק
*safek* or an אינה מגורשת einah megureshet. *aina megoreshet*. Okay so that's
where we left off. Now the interesting thing that we're going to
switch to today is that the end of the משנה Mishna *Mishnah*
says this idea of throwing the גט get. *get* and being it
near to her works not only in גירושין *geirushin* but it works
in קידושין *kiddushin* and paying back a debt. Now that's a big
חידוש chiddush *chiddush* because if it's within ארבע אמות arba amos *arba
amot* fine within ארבע אמות arba amos *arba amot* is a classic
קנין *kinyan* or at least a rabbinic קנין *kinyan*. But if it's
רבי Rabbi יוחנן'ס *Rabbi Yochanan's* idea that it doesn't have to be
in my four אמות amos *amot* I just have to be in
a position to guard it and protect it so then why does
that work for קידושין *kiddushin*? Why does it work for paying back
a debt? Since when is that a type of a קנין *kinyan*
that works in normal places? So that's what the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara*
turns to. Let's take a look. The bottom third of עין חית
עמוד בית *Ayin Chet Amud Bet*. וכן לעניין קידושין *V'chein L'Inyan Kiddushin*.
אמר רבי Rabbi אסי אמר רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan לגיטין אמרו ולא
לדבר אחר *Amar Rabbi Assi Amar Rabbi Yochanan L'Gittin Amru V'Lo L'Davar
Achar*. Yeah yeah it doesn't work for anything other than גיטין Gittin
*Gittin*. Okay sort of ignoring the משנה Mishna *Mishnah* but going with
the idea that this whole thing is a weird exception it only
works for גיטין Gittin, *Gittin*. Okay איתיביה רבי Rabbi אבא לרבי אסי
*Eitivei Rabbi Abba L'Rabbi Assi*. רבי Rabbi, אבא אמר לרבי
אסי *Rabbi Abba Amar L'Rabbi Assi* וכן לעניין קידושין *V'chein L'Inyan Kiddushin*.
What do you mean you ignoring the end of the משנה Mishna
*Mishnah* you said oh yeah this is a nice משנה Mishna *Mishnah*
but it's only about a גט get, *get*. The משנה Mishna. *Mishnah*
says it works for קידושין *kiddushin*. So שאני התם דכתיב ויצאה והיתה
*Shani Hasam D'chetiv V'Yatza V'Hayata*. You can't ask me about קידושין *kiddushin*.
קידושין *Kiddushin* is linked to גירושין *geirushin* it says she leaves her
husband and she marries another guy so therefore if it works for
גירושין *geirushin* it works for קידושין *kiddushin*. Now that actually
raises an interesting question about קידושין *kiddushin*. How much is קידושי כסף
*kiddushei kesef* the giving of
money or there are weird things that go on by קידושי כסף
*kiddushei kesef* like if I can
say with the benefit that you'll receive that I'll put in a
good word for you with your employer? Okay so that would actually
work בההיא הנאה *bahahi hana'ah* right? She doesn't take possession of any
object just some abstract benefit comes her way and that could be
an act of קידושין *kiddushin*. There are times I might not even
have to own the object to do קידושין *kiddushin* could be if
I steal an object and give it to her and she has
certain rights to it even if she obviously doesn't own it that's
a type of a קידושין *kiddushin*. So קידושין *kiddushin* is a little
weird too it's not like normal קנין *kinyan* like גיטין *Gittin*. So
what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is saying is you know what? If
by גט get *get* you don't have to do a full act
of a קנין *kinyan* it's enough to be protected and guarded or
whatever we understand is going on in the משנה Mishnah, *Mishnah* קידושין
*kiddushin* might be the same. It's still weird it doesn't work by
normal things but it could work by קידושין *kiddushin* if it works
by גיטין *Gittin*. And you say throw me that basketball and I'll
be מקודשת *mekudeshet* to you and I throw it across the basketball
court and it falls in a place where she can protect it
even if it's ten feet away from her she's מקודשת *mekudeshet*. Okay
the same way if I speak to her boss she's
מקודשת *mekudeshet*. It's a weird idea but it works by גיטין *Gittin*
and it works by קידושין *kiddushin*.
That's a big deal with the עדי קידושין *eidei kiddushin*.
Right right right I know. Why
does the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* say that in the end she's got
to have the גט get, *get* go directly into her hand? Okay
איתיביה *Eitivei* so anyway
so no קידושין *kiddushin* is like גיטין *Gittin*. ויצאה והיתה *V'yatza V'hayata*.
איתיביה *Eitivei*
you see I liked my basketball example because my basketball example the
thing doesn't break when you throw it and you
gotta. We don't have to see the positive effect. If it's something
that you're doing that I would like you to do for my
behalf, right? If it's something that, you know, I would, I would
essentially in theory pay for even, so it doesn't matter that she
actually some actual concrete benefit accrues to her. Okay, okay,
איתיבי, I'll ask you on this: וכן לעניין חוב. vechen l'inyan chov.
Okay, but the end of משנה Mishnah. says it also works for
paying back a debt. So again, we- it seems like this works
in classic קניינים. kinyanim זרוק לי חובי וזרקו לו, קרוב למלווה זכה
לו. Zrok li chovi v'zarko lo, karov l'malveh zachah lo.
If he throws it and it gets near the creditor, again which
near might be ארבע אמות, arba amos but here the חידוש chiddush.
is, or the reason why it's given as a תוספת, tosefes, presumably
means even without ארבע אמות, arba amos. it's near him, close to
him that he can protect it,
then the לוה loveh has paid back his debt. קרוב ללוה, Karov
l'loveh, if it's, however, nearer or under the protection of the לוה,
loveh, הלוה חייב, haloveh chayav, then the לוה loveh has not paid
back his debt and he's still- and he's still responsible if something
happens to the money. מחצה על מחצה, שניהם יחלוקו. Mechtzah al mechtzah,
shneihem yachloku.
They divide it, meaning if something happens to the money, he's- he
has to pay back half the debt. So anyway, you see that
it works by paying back a debt. It works in classic cases.
So the גמרא Gemara says, no, הכא במאי עסקינן דאמר ליה זרוק
לי חובי ותיפטר. hacha b'mai askinan d'amar lei zrok li chovi v'tipater.
No, no, no. Basically, the creditor said, if it was a normal
thing about 'pay me back my debt' and the guy threw it,
it wouldn't count. But if he said, 'throw it to me and
in the act of throwing it to me, you will be exempt
from paying the debt,' so then it works. So basically, okay, but
then you're saying that it's not the real paying of the debt,
it's just like the guy made a- the guy made a condition.
I know,
once you throw it to me, you're done. So if that's what
you said, of course it's going to work. That's not a חידוש.
chiddush So asks the גמרא, Gemara's אי הכי מאי למימרא? ei hachi
mai l'memra? Of course, if that's what the guy said and you
did it, so of course it's going to work. That's not fundamentally
saying it's a way of paying back a debt. So the גמרא
Gemara says, no, לא צריכא דאמר ליה זרוק לי חובי בתורת גיטין.
lo tzricha d'amar lei zrok li chovi b'toras gittin. Okay, no. Throw
me my גט get, and it will- and in the way- in
the way you would give a גט. get, Throw me my money!
Throw me my debt as if- throw me my debt and give
it to me in the way you would give a גט. get
Like, completely- really? That's the case of the משנה? Mishnah Oh my
God. Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara still says, והשתא מאי למימרא? v'hashta
mai l'memra? Big deal! So what? So he made a weird condition
and now you're telling me- if you do it, it works for
גט, get it works for this because that's what he said. So
the גמרא Gemara says, no, מהו דתימא מכי אמר ליה משחק אני
בך קא משמע לן. mahu d'teima mechi amar lei meshachek ani bach
ka mashma lan. Yeah, I was just kidding. I didn't mean it.
That's not really paying a debt back. So קא משמע לן, ka
mashma lan, if you made- if you said it, you said it
and it's binding. Again, that has got to be the worst read
ever of a משנה, Mishnah. right? The משנה Mishnah, says, 'this also
works by paying back a debt' and it says, 'yeah, it doesn't
work by paying back a debt.' What it means is, if the
guy makes this weird condition and you satisfy his condition, then it'll
be fine. But fundamentally, it does not work for paying back a
debt. So what you see is, it is such a bad textual
read of the משנה Mishnah. and nevertheless, you know, who is this?
רב אסי Rav Assi in the name of רבי Rebbi יוחנן cannot-
is so much willing to force that into the משנה Mishnah. because
cannot accept that this is a normal קניין. kinyan. Remember, it's the
same רבי יוחנן who said yesterday, earlier on this דף, daf, that
it does not have to be in the ארבע אמות, arba amos?
that it works by a גט get even if it's a hundred
אמות amos away if she can protect it. So he is- if
that's what works by a גט, get there is no way it
can work by paying back a loan. And therefore, he will force
a very, very difficult read in the משנה Mishnah because he's willing
to make such a חידוש chiddush. by גט, get, he's willing- and
then he says, well, I can't say it by anything else. So
I'm going to have to- have to have a crazy read of
the משנה. Mishnah. All right, is that clear what's being said? Okay,
now I do want to say by the way, bracketing the גמרא's
Gemara answer, a debt is still different- paying back a debt is
still different than giving- than selling you an object. Right? If I'm
selling you an object, this basketball, it's not yours and I want
it to become yours, so you have to do an act of
taking possession: take it up, have it in your yard, have it
in your ארבע אמות. arba amos Just throwing it near you won't
work. But a debt, fundamentally the money is owed to you. So
this hundred dollars, for example, is not the same hundred dollars you
gave me, but fundamentally is it the same idea that you have
to do a מעשה קניין maaseh kinyan on the hundred dollars? Right?
I mean, I am basically giving it back and once I give
it back, I- we've given you back something that was coming your-
that was deserving to you and coming to you. Right, but I'm
just saying it's an interesting question. Put this גמרא Gemara aside. For
to me to say I paid you back your debt, do you
have to do the exact מעשה קניין? maaseh kinyan? Let me give
you an example. Let's say I paid you back a- let's say
we say that הגבהה hagbahah requires three טפחים tefachim off the ground,
okay? And my- I owe you, Michael, a hundred dollars and I
put it, you know, in your- well, hand might not be הגבהה-
hagbahah I put it on the ground and I say, 'here, I'm
paying it back to you,' and you start picking it off the
ground, and before it gets three טפחים, tefachim, it- it burns, okay?
It blows up in flames. You say, 'I didn't do a הגבהה,
hagbahah, you still have to pay me my money.' Presumably- not, right?
Presumably—I don't know, but I'm saying—But it didn't—we
mean to protect the guy who lent the money, and we say
that doesn't work?
I understand. So you're saying, practically it's only fair that this guy
gets some protection. But the question is what degree of protection do
you need? Is it—it's a little bit different than taking possession of
something which was never mine. It's taking something that is paying back
and giving me something that was owed to me. So I'm just
saying it is an interesting question whether, right, you need the exact
same thing for מעשה קנין ma'aseh kinyan though, again, I would agree
with you, it would probably be much closer to a מעשה קנין
ma'aseh kinyan than the types of things that we're talking about. That
would be true, yes.
So what is it? משטה אני בך? meshauteh ani bach? In other
words, you—your words are kidding. Right, I understand. I was just kidding,
but still you still owe me the money.
You didn't really pay me back the money. So that's a general
question. When does somebody say a verbal type of a thing in
a transaction and when can he say I wasn't serious or not
and sometimes you need the presence of עדים edim or a מעשה
קנין ma'aseh kinyan or other types of things. Okay, let's take—let's see
as the גמרא Gemara continues. Okay. אמר רב חסדא, Amar Rav Chisda,
said רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, גט בידה ומשיחה בידו. Get beyada umeshicha
beyado. Now, he has she—he throws—he gives her the גט, get but
he's holding on to the strings. You ever heard the expression no
strings attached? This is a גט get with strings attached. Literally. Okay?
It's funny, it's exactly that idea. He gives her the גט get
and he's holding on to the string. Okay. אם יכול לנתקו ולהביאו
אצלו אינה מגורשת. Im yachol lenatko ulehivio etzlo einah megureshet. If by
he could yank the string and take the גט get to him,
she's not divorced. Because then he has not fully given it to
her, he still has his claws in it. ואם לאו, Ve'im lav,
but if he's just holding on to the string but it means
nothing, he cannot bring it back to him, so she's fully in
possession of it, מגורשת, megureshet, she's divorced.
You think—do you think this is literal or it is—It is literal.
I mean obviously it serves a metaphorical purpose, but it's literal. מאי
טעמא, Mai ta'ama, what's the reason? בעינן כריתות וליכא. Ba'inan krisus veleika.
It needs to divide the two. So if they're still not fully
divided,
if he in theory could yank it back, that's not a full
division. Okay. אמר רב יהודה, Amar Rav Yehuda, הייתה ידה עשויה כטפרס.
Haysah yada asuya ketafres. If her hand was made, thank you, like
a—like a slope, like a—your hands are—are a slippery slope. Okay. So
she makes her hands like sloped down, angled down, thank you, הייתה
ידה עשויה כטפרס. Haysah yada asuya ketafres. וזרק לה, Vezarak lah,
and threw the גט get into her hand, and what happened? אף
על פי שהגיע לידה אינה מגורשת. Af al pi shehigi'a leyada einah
megureshet. It hit her hands and then it falls out of her
hands, right? Her hands are like this, right? So it hits her
hands and it falls—and it falls out. So אינה מגורשת. Einah Megureshet.
Like football. It's not considered to be in possession
of—well, you see, that's a metaphor I don't have so well. אמאי
הא קנפי לה בארבע אמות דידה קנפי? Amai ha kenafei lah be'arba
amos didah kenafei? So now the גמרא Gemara is still working with
this ארבע אמות arba amos idea. It says I get that when
it hits her hand she's not מגורשת, megureshes. but when it hits
the ground she should be because it fell within her ארבע אמות
arba amos and within her ארבע אמות arba amos, works. So the
גמרא Gemara says, דלא נח. delo nach. Okay, it did
not—it did not settle, which רש״י Rashi basically means which, yeah, before
it—it could have—What?
It dropped and then it rolled away.
Right, rolled, that's going to be a question. But anyway, but—but basically
רש״י Rashi says that before it hit the ground, like a wind
blew it away, something, okay, out of her ארבע אמות. arba amos.
And רש״י Rashi even says it blew up in flames, I don't
know how it spontaneously combusted. Okay, but it fell out of her
hand, did not hit the ground before it flew away or before
it burnt. דלא נח, Delo nach, it did not come to rest.
ותתגרש מאוירא דארבע אמות? Utisgaresh me'avira de'arba amos? But still from the
airspace of the ארבע אמות? arba amos So the same way if
something comes in the airspace of your yard, which we'll see in
a minute on—when we get to today's דף, daf so if the
ארבע אמות arba amos? is considered to be even like in רשות
הרבים reshus harabbim, is considered to be right now the ארבע אמות
arba amos. where you're standing, like your little space and your yard,
so maybe the airspace also works for you. תיפשוט דבעי רבי אלעזר,
Tifshot deba'ei Rabbi Elazar, let's use this to—to—to resolve the question that
רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar raised.
דבעי רבי אלעזר, Deba'ei Rabbi Elazar, ארבע אמות שאמרו, arba amos she'amru,
when the Rabbis said you had four אמות ammot for קניינים kinyanim
in רשות הרבים, reshus ha-rabbin. יש להן אויר אין להן אויר? yesh
lahen avir ein lahen avir? Does it include airspace or not? So
תיפשוט דאין להן אויר, tifshot de'ein lahen avir, since it says it
does not work, we should presume that there is no airspace, because
you're telling me that even though it fell out of her hands
and into the airspace of the ארבע אמות Arba amos it does
not work. So the גמרא Gemara says, no. הכא במאי עסקינן בעומדת
על גב הנהר. Hacha bemai askinan be'omedet al gav hanahar. No, no,
no, she's standing by the edge of the river. So, here she
is right at the river's edge and her hands are like this.
So as soon as it falls out of her hand, it goes
over the air of the river. So even if the river's within
your ארבע אמות, arba amos you do not have the airspace above
the river because it's not a type of a place that something
can ever come to rest in. So it's not a type of
a place, if the ground is not a place that something can
come to rest in, the airspace above it also does not work.
Wait a minute. So דמעיקרא לאיבוד קאי. demi'ikara le'ibud ka'ei. From the
very outset when the גט, get you know, when the גט get?
rolled off her hands, it was heading straight for the river, so
that's never considered to be under her protection or in her protected
space.
Yeah, maybe, but it never stopped and it rolled away out of,
you know, outside from...
Right, so that's a question, yeah, so that's a question too, something
that's rolling and if it doesn't... Yeah, I mean it's a question.
You're right. The גמרא Gemara, could have said that
but, you know, the fact I would agree with you that the
fact that the גמרא Gemara did not say that suggests that that
would work, because the גמרא Gemara. didn't say that as an answer.
Okay. What?
Which is interesting.
Yeah, I know, it's a discussion, it's discussed in שבת, Shabbos, it's
discussed by other things. Okay. Yes, it's discussed by מציעא, Metziah, something
coming in one door and going out the other. Okay, let's take
a look now at the next משנה, Mishnah getting to the official
דף of today, ע"ט. Ayin Tes. Okay.
האי Hais משנה. Mishnah היתה עומדת על ראש הגג Haiso omedes al
rosh ha-gag she's standing on the top of her rooftop. וזרקו לה
V'zarkulah and the guy is down at the ground level, her rooftop,
and he throws it up to her. Okay. כיון שהגיע לאויר הגג
Keivan she-higia l'avir ha-gag once it got into the airspace of the
rooftop. So here we're back to the idea of airspace. She owns
the roof, so she owns the airspace above it. Okay, so that's
in her yard. הרי זו מגורשת Harei zu megureshes she's divorced.
Weird, if he's
from above and it falls back down?
No, so the גמרא Gemara is going to ask that. Presumably not.
Presumably it's going over the airspace and it's going to land. But
as soon as it hits the airspace... Yeah, the roofs are flat.
Yeah, yeah, thank you for pointing that out. The roofs are flat.
It's going over the airspace, even before it lands, it's going to
land, but before it lands it's already מגורשת. Megureshet? But wait, no.
Let's say again, it spontaneously combusted or let's say a dog came
and, you know, snatched it, or a wind came and blew it
away. So it doesn't matter. It had been in her airspace. It
was, now we're going to see in the גמרא, Gemara it probably...
yeah, well, the גמרא's Gemara going to ask, sort of ask that.
But for now let's presume it was in her airspace, under normal
circumstances it would have come to rest, so she's divorced once it's
in her airspace even if something happened and it did not come
to rest.
Which is what we were trying to figure out a second ago
about whether...
That's ארבע אמות. arba amot. You certainly have the airspace of your
own property. That's just the Rabbinic ארבע אמות arba amot? you might
not have the airspace. Okay. הוא מלמעלה והיא מלמטה Hu mi-lemala v'hi
mi-lemata he's on the roof above and she's below. וזרקו לה V'zarkulah
and threw it to her. כיון שיצא מרשות הגג Keivan she-yatza me-reshus
ha-gag once it went over the lip of the roof, right, so
now it's in the airspace of the courtyard, of the yard below.
Is it within her ארבע אמות?
None of this is in her ארבע אמות. ארבע אמות is... don't
get confused, ארבע אמות is a הלכה halacha in רשות הרבים. reshut
harabbim This is a real issue of being in your yard. Okay.
תוספות Tosafot reminds us that according to one אמורא amora earlier she
doesn't even have to be standing on the roof, right? Remember, it's
in her yard. That's the issue. So this is just taking the
idea that she קונה kona it when it's in her yard, even
when it's in the airspace of the yard or of the roof.
כיון שיצא מרשות הגג Keivan she-yatza me-reshus ha-gag once it went outside
of the domain of the roof and is now over the airspace
of the yard, and she owns the yard. נמחק או נשרף Nimchak
o nisraf if it gets erased or burnt. Again, I don't know
how those things happen. Well, it could get erased if all of
a sudden it starts pouring, okay, and before it hit the ground
it got erased. I don't know how it gets... some fire, I
don't know how it burns in mid-air. Anyway, הרי זו מגורשת. harei
zu megureshes. Okay. Somebody is passing by holding a torch or something.
Okay, she's divorced. The easiest scenario is that it blows away anyway.
Yeah.
Let's
take a look at the גמרא. Gemara והא V'ha says גמרא Gemara
לא מינטר... lo mintar... So the גמרא Gemara asks Michael's question. Michael,
I mean you've written the script for the גמרא Gemara there. Okay.
So what do you mean? It's not protected, meaning the גמרא Gemara
understands that the roof doesn't even have a fence. It's a flat
roof with no fence. So it might be over the airspace but
remember the whole idea we mentioned before is חצר המשתמרת. chatzer ha-mishtameres.
Things that are... so if it's an airspace that fundamentally, things that
are in the airspace are not necessarily... I mean gravity might bring
them down but there's nothing that somehow keeps them in that space,
okay, then that's not considered like it's protected, like it's in that
space, right? There's no walls, there's no whatever. So the גמרא Gemara
says, let's see what the גמרא Gemara says,
okay, one minute.
Okay, fine. So the
גמרא Gemara says אמר רב פפא בגג שיש לו מעקה עסקינן amar
Rav Papa: Begag she-yesh lo ma'akeh askinan and it's got a roof
around it, so it's considered to be a fence... sorry, it's got
a fence around it, okay. So once it gets, presumably what that
means is and then it presumably also in,
you know,
it's within the fence, it's not above the fence, so therefore that's
considered to be sort of like protected
from outside things.
It's not yet on the ground but it's sloped down and it's
like... the fence is ten feet high, she's now eight feet high
in
the air... or just well above it then the area...
So first of all, okay, first of all let's just talk. The
גמרא Gemara says about a חצר המשתמרת... chatzer ha-mishtameres... If this is
just your normal yard, okay, and there’s no fence around it, and
some things—the basketball—goes into the yard or whatever it is, okay.
Hold on, oh you mean because of the הלכה halacha that you
have to make a fence around your thing? Yeah, right. But wait,
wait, let's just let me just first let me start with point
number one, okay? You like, because you all, you guys so much
liked my 3D drawings yesterday. Okay, so חצר נשמרת, Chatzer Nishmeret, this
is not a חצר נשמרת. Chatzer Nishmeret. Throw me your basketball into
my yard, I'll be קונה koneh it. You're not קונה koneh because
it's in my yard but it's not protected. Anybody can come and
grab it if I wasn't standing there. Unless you're within—not—yeah. Okay, we're
not talking about ארבע אמות. Unless I was standing there, somebody could
come and and take it away.
So just because it's—even though it's a רשות היחיד? Reshut HaYachid?
Yeah, yeah, yeah. So that's—but the point we haven't been emphasizing, I
mean we said a lot, נשמרת לדעתה nishmeret l'da'atah and all those
types of things, and maybe if you're there maybe it's obviously different,
okay, but let's say you're not there and you just, I mean
or whatever, let's ignore for a moment that question, okay? Is just
because your thing is in my yard, if it's not protected in
my yard, you need חצר נשמרת. Chatzer Nishmeret. Okay, well—what?
Why does it need a fence? Well, why is it theft if
somebody comes into my yard?
Well, it's a little bit of a circular question. It would only
be a theft if I owned it. And so for me to
be defined as owning it, if you're throwing me your basketball, you
have to give it to me in a way that I can
protect it against—that it's protected against other people. You know what I'm
saying? Right, if I were to own it and somebody were to
come into my yard, this
is my yard, I understand, okay?
I mean you're trespassing, right, and
you're
trespassing—so that's—that's an interesting question. If the reality is that people are
afraid to go into other people's yards because they'll be recorded or
because they're afraid they'll be caught by the police or other types
of things, would that be enough to define something as נשמרת? nishmeret?
I don't know the answer to that, okay? But the basic idea
is that even if it's in your yard, if there—if there's nothing
protecting it, keeping it—other people away from it, right, that's not considered
like you're in enough control, okay? You need the idea of נשמרת.
nishmeret. So similarly—people tell me that the green for whatever does not
erase well. Okay, anyway, similarly if it's on your rooftop, okay,
it's the same הלכה. halacha. The גמרא Gemara says that once—you know,
now, you know, I mean it's an interesting idea because you could
sort of say that like who's going to get to the top
of the roof? Exactly. But the גמרא Gemara says, here's the גט
get. flying over the rooftop, okay, nothing is—nothing is keeping it in
that space, protecting it in that space, okay? A wind could come
and—so maybe a person can't, Superman can come and fly and get
it, but okay, a wind could come and blow it away. What?
Pass around, say a bird.
Oh, that's true. Anyway, so that's the question. That's—it might be over
the airspace, but it's not נשמר nishmar in the airspace against things
that could make it go away, like wind. So the גמרא Gemara
anyway says, you've got your fence, okay, we'll draw it like this,
okay. You've got your fence here, okay, but then it's really not
that it goes over the airspace, it would actually have to go
into the space right of the fence. It would have to go
in there, and then it's נשמר. nishmar. Okay, right. So if the
fence is
10 feet high, the גט get. has to be like 8 feet
high in it.
Yeah, yeah, yeah. The גט get. has to be, right, like low—right,
right. So the משנה Mishnah. doesn't sound that way so much.
But only if the walls of the building itself leading up to
the top of the roof doesn't serve to make it נשמרת. nishmeret.
Oh, that's like a סוכה sukkah question. Well, it's נשמרת nishmeret against
people below, but it's not נשמרת nishmeret against things that happen to
things on rooftops, like
it's not blowing away.
Right, well, the fence isn't going to help for that. Okay, anyway.
Okay, anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says like this,
עולא בר מנשיא משמיה דאבימי אמר הכא בפחות משלושה סמוך לגג עסקינן
דכל פחות משלושה סמוך לגג כגג דמי. Ulla bar Manashya mishmei d'Avimi
amar hacha b'pachot mishlosha samuch legag askinan d'chol pachot mishlosha samuch legag
k'gag dami.
Okay, so he says it's within
three of the roof, three טפחים tfachim of the roof. So even
with no fence, if it's right here and within three, so when
we say as soon as the גט get. stays there, it doesn't
mean it's way up here, it means it went over the lip
and it's within three טפחים, tfachim, so it's like it's on the
ground itself. So here actually is interesting, right? If it was a
case of my yard being on the ground as I just said
wouldn't be enough unless I've got—it's somehow my yard is protected, you
know, because somebody can come and take it. But here, right, we're
not really like afraid as you said of people coming up and
taking it, so if it's actually on the ground it works, but
as long as it's not up in the air. Because up in
the air wouldn't be good because it's not really contained within the—within
the area if it's higher up in the air.
Yeah, does it make a difference to say it's like a partnership?
Like you know, like a bunch of people—maybe—live on the
rooftop, or it's only yours? Maybe. Well, I mean, well if it's
not only yours, there obviously would be different. But we'll get something
similar to that in a minute. Let's take a look. הוא מלמעלה
והיא מלמטה, Hu milma'ala v'hee milmata, he's above and she's below. So
the גמרא Gemara says והא לא מינטר, v'ha lo mintar, same thing.
When you throw it down, right, it's still in mid-air, there's nothing
that is sort of, you know, protected. Protecting it and keeping it
in that space. Okay, again, the fact that maybe gravity is bringing
it down is not enough. It's not considered held in that space.
So the
גמרא Gemara says אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל כגון שהיו מחיצות התחתונות
עודפות על העליונות Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Shmuel kegon shehayu mechitzot hatachtonot
odofot al haelyonot that the outer ones are higher than the yard
are higher than the walls of the roof. The way one way
תוספות describes this, which I think is the easiest way to understand
this
is, it's a building
in the middle of the yard. Okay, so if that's the building
in the middle of the
yard and here the guy is throwing the גט get. and the
walls of the yard are higher than the building, right, then as
soon as it leaves the rooftop it's contained within the walls of
the yard. Okay. What? He lives in a fortress?
Something like that, yeah. Well, maybe a chain link fence or something.
Well, what would be more likely is if there's taller buildings around.
Oh, that could be.
Like there's two story buildings, I mean a skyscraper.
Right, right, right, right, right, that could be.
But by the way, I think you should note that this must
be the source of the expression things are still up in the
air.
There you
go, together with strings being attached.
Okay. כגון שהיו מחיצות התחתונות עודפות על העליונות. kegon shehayu mechitzot hatachtonot
odofot al haelyonot. וכן אמר רבי אלעזר אמר רבי אושעיא כגון שהיו
מחיצות התחתונות עודפות על העליונות. vechen amar Rabbi Elazar amar Rabbi Oshaya
kegon shehayu mechitzot hatachtonot odofot al haelyonot. וכן אמר רבי אמי אמר
רבי יוחנן כגון שהיו מחיצות התחתונות עודפות על העליונות. vechen amar Rabbi
Ami amar Rabbi Yochanan kegon shehayu mechitzot hatachtonot odofot al haelyonot. So
that went fast.
אמר ליה רב פפא לאביי Amar lei Rav Pappa leAbaye כמאן כרבי?
keman keRabbi? Is this going like רבי דאמר קלוטה כמי שהונחה דמיא?
deamar kluta kemi shehuncha damya?
That רבי said, now we're starting to, before we were talking about
the קניינים kinyanim? model, now we can talk about a שבת Shabbat
model. If I throw an object from רשות הרבים reshus harabim into
רשות היחיד reshut hayachid and when am I transgressing שבת? Shabbat? When
it lands? רבי says as long as it gets into the air
space of the רשות היחיד, reshut hayachid, if it's קלוטה, kluta, if
it's like absorbed by the space, it's like it's on the ground.
So he's saying, is that what we're saying here? That the same
way that works by שבת Shabbat here it works even before it's
landed? Now of course that's an interesting question. Why are you asking
by שבת? Shabbat? Like would this work by קניינים? kinyanim If I
wanted to sell you my basketball, could I throw it off the
roof and it gets into your airspace? Presumably yes. The גמרא Gemara
discusses that by קניינים kinyanim. about an אבידה aveida rolling through my
yard or something. Anyway, that's his question. His question is from שבת.
Shabbat. One minute, by שבת Shabbat only רבי says that if it's
in the air space you're חייב. chayav. So
the גמרא Gemara says אמר ליה אפילו תימא רבנן amar lei afilu
tima rabbanan even the רבנן rabbanan that argue on רבי, עד כאן
לא פליגי רבנן עליה דרבי אלא לעניין שבת. ad kan lo peligi
rabbanan alei deRabbi ella leinyan Shabbat. By שבת, Shabbat, is that considered
like it landed in רשות היחיד? reshut hayachid? אבל הכא משום מינטר
הוא. aval hacha mishum mintar hu. Here it's about being protected. Like
רבי יוחנן even a hundred אמות away it's protected. So even though
here it's an idea of being in the רשות, reshut, okay, still,
what's enough in the רשות, reshut, the air space to be considered
like it's an act of giving a גט? get, But it's protected
in the air space. והא קמינטר veha kamintar it's protected.
So
it's okay that it's in the air space as long as you've
got higher walls around it. Okay. Now the גמרא Gemara says like
this. נמחק, nimchak, if it gets erased while it's in
midair, she's still divorced once it fell into
a
protected airspace. אמר רב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה Amar Rav Nachman
amar Rabbah bar Avuha לא שנו אלא שנמחק דרך ירידה. lo shanu
ella shenimchak derech yerida. אבל נמחק דרך עלייה לא. aval nimchak derech
aliya lo. מאי טעמא? mai taama? מעיקרא לא למנח קאי. meikara lo
leminach kai. Let's say,
right, let's take this case which is even more of a חידוש.
Here you are, as soon as it leaves the airspace of the
roof, right, it's in protected airspace of the outer courtyard. Nevertheless, if
it was thrown upward, okay, then its trajectory is upward, even if
eventually gravity will bring it down. You cannot define it when it's
in a, what's it called, an exit trajectory? What's that called when
they send out the
spaceship? Exit velocity I think it is. Anyway, when it's on an
exit trajectory, even if you know that gravity is going to bring
it down before it leaves, okay, it is not defined. consider now
that it's being in the yard because its direction is heading away
from the yard. Okay, it's only considered to be present and protected
and in that yard when it is
actually falling down. Or I imagine if it was going straight it
probably also would be.
Okay, נמחק Nimchak on the way up, right, אינה מגורשת. einah megureshet.
If
it is נמחק Nimchak halfway in the middle of its downwards fall,
she's...
yeah, right. I wonder what would be if I threw it directly
horizontally directly parallel to the ground, I don't know.
Does it go parallel here? Yeah. What? Goal... very
good.
Spell that out for me, I don't know that.
That's very good.
Meaning if someone's shooting and the ball's on its upward trajectory and
you knock it out of the way, that's a block. No, goaltending
is when it's going down. Right.
You can
block it but once it's already on its way down, that's it,
you can't.
I see,
I see. And let's say somebody jumped as high as the basket
and threw it horizontally...
anyway, because you anyway don't have the middle case here. All right,
but that's a good parallel. Okay. נשרף Nisraf if it burnt. אמר
רב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה Amar Rav Nachman Amar Rabbah Bar
Avuha לא שנו אלא שקדם גט לדליקה. Lo Shanu Ela She-Kadam Get
Le-Dleikah. When is it if it burnt, if now we hear it's
in the air space, it's the protected air space, there are fences
around it, it's on its way down and if it burns you're
מגורשת? Megureshet. If it was thrown off the roof before the fire
broke out. אבל קדמה דליקה לגט, Aval Kadmah Dleikah Le-Get, if there
was a fire below when it was thrown off the roof... okay,
so right, לא Lo that would not be מגורשת. megureshet מאי טעמא
מעיקרא לשריפה קאזיל? Mai Ta'ama Me-Ikra Le-Sreifah Ka-Azil? That was never going
into a yard, that was to be being thrown to get burnt.
Okay, אמר רב חסדא... Amar Rav Chisda...
he threw it the other way?
You mean a wind came and blew it around? Oh that probably
would be okay. I think that would be considered קדם גט לדליקה
Kadam Get Le-Dleikah that it's like the way it's been thrown has
nothing to do with the דליקה. Dleikah. Right, if the guy has
a barbecue on this side and I'm throwing it on that side
and the wind whips it around, yeah, it's not קדמה. Kadmah. Yeah,
exactly. Okay. אמר רב חסדא Amar Rav Chisda רשויות חלוקות בגיטין. Reshuyos
Chalukos Be-Gittin. Let's say
there are... he says, the... there's... you've got your... you've got your
building and there's another building here, okay, in the courtyard, and this
one is owned by whatever, you know, let's
say it's the case where it's going to her, and this this
thing is owned by somebody else, this is owned by a nice
family down here, okay, or it's owned by him. Okay, so he
says, the fact that there's different, there's a different, even though on
the top it looks like a flat roof, the fact that below,
right, this is owned by a different person, that means that this
space above is not her. It's... it separates the space for גיטין.
Now we're going to spell out what that means. Okay, רשויות חלוקות
בגיטין. Reshuyos Chalukos Be-Gittin. אמר ליה רמי בר חמא לרבא Amar Lei
Rami Bar Chama Le-Rava for anything else too? Yeah, well we're going
to see. Right.
מנא ליה לסבא הא?
Mina
Lei Le-Saba Ha?
Where do you know this from?
It's again, remember that by גיטין you might not need a formal
קנין the same way
in
other places. מנא ליה לסבא הא? Mina Lei Le-Saba Ha? Where do
you know this from? אמר ליה... Amar Lei...
respectful way?
Yeah, I think so. אמר ליה מתניתין היא, Amar Lei Masnitin Hi,
it's our משנה. Mishnah היתה עומדת על ראש הגג וזרקו לה כיון
שהגיע גט לאויר הגג הרי זו מגורשת. Haitah Omedes Al Rosh Ha-Gag
Ve-Zarko Lah Keivan She-Higia Get Le-Avir Ha-Gag Harei Zu Megureshet. But now,
במה עסקינן? Bemai Askinnan? What are we talking about? אילימא בגג דידה
וחצר דידה, Ilima Be-Gag Didah Ve-Chatzer Didah,
who owns the roof and who owns the yard below? If she
owns the roof and she owns the yard, למה לי אויר גג?
Lamah Li Avir Gag? Why does it have to get to the
roof? Right, it's all her. The yard below is hers as well.
אלא בגג דידיה וחצר דידיה, Ela Be-Gag Didei Ve-Chatzer Didei, let's say
it's his roof and his yard. כי הגיע לאויר גג מאי הוי?
Ki Higia Le-Avir Gag Mai Havei? So what good does it do
to get to the roof? אלא פשיטא, Ela Peshita, clearly what's going
on in the משנה, Mishnah בגג דידה וחצר דידיה. Be-Gag Didah Ve-Chatzer
Didei. It's her roof and his yard. That's when he's throwing it
to the roof. Fine, that's the רישא Reisha of the משנה. Mishnah
אימא סיפא, Eima Seifa, let's look at the end of the משנה.
Mishnah הוא מלמעלה והיא מלמטה, Hu Milmalah Ve-Hi Milmatah, he's above and
she's below, וזרקו לה, Ve-Zarko Lah, and he threw it to her,
כיון שיצא מרשות הגג, Keivan She-Yatza Me-Reshus Ha-Gag, once it left the
rooftop, נמחק או נשרף הרי זו מגורשת, Nimchak O Nisraf Harei Zu
Megureshet, she's divorced even if it gets burnt. Now again, who owns
what? ואי בגג דידה וחצר דידיה, Ve-I Be-Gag Didah Ve-Chatzer Didei, if
it's like we described the first scenario, her roof and his yard,
אמאי מגורשת? Amai Megureshet? Why is she divorced when it goes off
of the rooftop? אלא בגג דידיה וחצר דידה, Ela Be-Gag Didei Ve-Chatzer
Didah, it must be the סיפא Seifa when he's above and she's
below also means that it's his roof and her yard. רישא בגג
דידה וחצר דידיה וסיפא בגג דידיה וחצר דידה? Reisha Be-Gag Didah Ve-Chatzer
Didei Ve-Seifa Be-Gag Didei Ve-Chatzer Didah? How can we be switching it?
How can you say in the beginning it's her roof and in
the end you say it's his roof? Now the obvious answer to
that is because by describing who's standing where, it implicitly tells you
who owns which space. But he says, no, it just describes where
they're standing. It doesn't make a difference in terms of... it doesn't
tell you that they're owning the spaces as different. So it's crazy.
Why is it in the רישא Reisha we're presuming it's her space
and in the סיפא Seifa we're presuming the roof is his space?
So the גמרא says, אלא לאו Ela Lav the only... The only
way to explain the משנה Mishnah. in a consistent סוגיא sugya is
דאושלה מקום. D'Oshla Makom. Remember like we said before? It's all his,
the yard, the rooftop, what he said to her was, I will
let you use the space that you're in for your קנין of
a גט. get What he's doing is it's like a real close,
if you want, it's a close reading of the משנה. Mishnah What
he is saying is, if you read the משנה closely, the משנה
does not speak about who owns what space. It only speaks about
where people are standing, right? Now, you or I could have said,
that's actually a great point. You or I could have said, you
know what? Maybe that's like the previous משנה. Remember the previous משנה
had them in רשות הרבים and it worked when it was קרוב
karov to her, right? So maybe this משנה has nothing to do
with whose roof it is and whose yard it is. It's just
where she's standing. Okay, so that's the first point he's making. So
he's saying oh, if it's where she's standing, though, he doesn't want
to say that it really doesn't matter completely who owns the space.
We'll assume it's all his space, but he's telling her you can
use the space you're standing in for your, for the purpose of
the גט. get, Okay, so he's like renting her the space.
Did he have to tell her that or is it assumed to
be?
It's a good question. It sounds like he told her that.
Okay, so then I think she was in between a private and
a public space in this instance, right?
Well no, this is all his now we're assuming.
And he's... What about the proximity idea? In other words, in the
public space we were saying
there's the קרוב, karov, it's proximity. Right, that's true, meaning the reason
to shift from the previous משנה is here it didn't use the
phrase of קרוב, karov, it started speaking about air space ideas, so
clearly it's more, it's a different sort of system that we're using
here. Right. Okay, so anyways, he says look, the משנה is only
talking about where they're standing. So it must be it's all his,
but he gave her permission to use the space. דחד מקום, D'chad
makom, and this is what we said before, מושלי אינשי, moshli inshi,
and we're going to presume that he only said you can use
one space. תרי מקומות לא מושלי אינשי, Trei mekomos lo moshli inshi.
not two. So basically what is he saying? He's saying, when she's
above, she doesn't own the building, he owns the building. But when
she's above, he said to her, you can use the space you're
in for גט. get So he basically was מקנה makneh her the
rooftop for her to use for her גט. get When she's below,
he was מקנה makneh her the yard to use for the גט.
get, Okay, but now what we're saying is, ah, but because it's
true that he was מקנה makneh her the space, what I'm going
to say is if this is a different building, even if it's
attached, conceptually this rooftop is a different space. So therefore she can
only use the rooftop of building one, he didn't tell her which
building, okay, it's not owned by a nice little family, it's all
owned by him. Okay, but he didn't tell her, he didn't tell
her which building, okay, he told her you can use a space.
So if she basically is on this rooftop, this thing over this
building, she can use this space, if it were thrown here it
would not work. Okay, even on the top it all looks like
one, but because below it's separate buildings, okay, so he only allowed
her to use one space and not two spaces. Okay.
השאלה Hashailah is like a לשון lashon מושאל mushal like another...
no, להשאיל. lehashil. שאלה. She'elah. Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Okay. Alright, so... okay... let's take a look.
So that says like this. Okay, so fine. תרי מקומות Trei mekomos
לא מושלי אינשי. lo moshli inshi,
Okay. אמר ליה, Amar lei, no, מידי איריא? midei irya? No, that's
not a proof that the case is switched from the רישא Reisha
to the סיפא. Seifa. דילמא הכי ודילמא הכי. Dilma hachi v'dilma hachi.
Okay. Yeah, they're different scenarios.
רישא, Reisha, each one is its own scenario. רישא בגג דידה וחצר
דידה. Reisha b'gag didah v'chatzer didah. In the beginning when she's on
the roof, the case is she owns the roof. וסיפא, V'seifa, and
in the end when he's on the roof, בגג דידיה וחצר דידה,
b'gag didei v'chatzer didah, he owns the roof and she owns the
yard. Okay, but that's interesting. I mean, that's a really interesting read
of the משנה. Besides the הלכה halacha of different buildings below, he's
saying I don't read this משנה that she owns the roof or
the yard. It's all his. It's just that she has the right,
and maybe Michael says maybe implicitly, not a clear, she has the
right to be using, he is giving her the right to use
the space she's in. And then we have to define what's considered
the same space or a different space. Okay. Now the גמרא says
like this. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, שלש מדות בגיטין. Shalosh middos b'gittin.
There are three sort of like principles by גט, get. sort of
when you compare what works by גט get, to what works or
doesn't work by other things. Now again, I would really like to
see it held up against what works by קניינים. kinyanim? A lot
of this comparison is going to be comparing it to what works
by שבת Shabbat to be considered, you know, transgressing שבת. Shabbat. Okay,
so... הא דאמר רבי, Ha d'amar Rebbi, קלוטה כמי שהונחה. keluta k'mi
shehunacha.
רבי says when it's absorbed in the space it's like it's on
the ground. If you throw it into רשות היחיד reshus hayachid it's
like it's on the רשות היחיד reshus hayachid and you've transgressed שבת
Shabbat even in the air space. ופליגי רבנן עליה, u'pligi rabanan alei,
but the רבנן rabanan disagree and say air space is not a
transgression of carrying on שבת Shabbat if it's like thrown into over
private property. הני מילי לענין שבת, Hani mili l'inyan Shabbat, the רבנן
rabanan only disagree for שבת Shabbat purposes. אבל הכא, Aval hacha, here,
משום נטורי הוא, mishum neturei hu, once it's in the air space...
airspace it's protected וכא מנטרי ליה veka minterei lei and it's protected
and that's enough. Again, could you please tell me what the הלכה
halacha would be by קניינים? Okay, but okay, anyway, moving on. והא
דאמר רב חסדא, Veha de'amar Rav Chisda, now let's take a flip
case, okay, where it's rested but it's not protected. One case is
it's not rested but it's protected, it's flying in the airspace, right?
The flip is, it's rested in the domain but not protected. What's
the case? דאמר רב חסדא De'amar Rav Chisda נעץ קנה ברשות היחיד.
na'atz kaneh bi'reshut hayachid. You put a long pole up in רשות
היחיד, reshut hayachid, like, you know, a hundred אמה amah pole, ובראשו
טרסקל, u'vi'rosho traskal,
and there's a basket at the top of this whole pole, okay?
וזרק ונח על גביו, ve'zarak ve'nach al gabav, and you threw something
a hundred אמה amah into the basket on this long pole hovering
above רשות היחיד, reshut hayachid, okay? אפילו גבוה מאה אמה afilu gavoah
me'ah amah even a hundred אמה amah חייב, chayav, you're חייב chayav
on שבת. Shabbat. So what's that case? It's resting in the airspace
of רשות היחיד, reshut hayachid, but it's not protected, right? It's way
up above any type of a fence. So in that, לפי שרשות
היחיד עולה עד לרקיע, lefi she'reshut hayachid olah ad l'raki'a, for שבת
Shabbat purposes, רשות היחיד reshut hayachid goes all the way up to
heaven. So it's resting but it's not protected, it's the exact mirror
image of the previous case. So הני מילי לעניין שבת, hani milei
l'inyan Shabbat, there you're חייב chayav for שבת Shabbat because it's rested
even though it's not protected. אבל הכא aval hacha by גט, get
משום נטורי הוא, mishum neturai hu,
it doesn't work for גט because a גט is about being in
a space that is protected and that's not protected. Okay, so you
get how these are mirror images of one another? Right? One is
it's not rested but it is protected, works for גט, not for
שבת. Shabbat. The other is rested but not protected, works for שבת,
Shabbat, does not work for גט. Yes.
Wouldn't you think that something that high up by definition is a
type of protection?
No, so that goes to the point we were saying before, it's
not protected from the things that, you know,
it's only protected by happenstance because people don't get there, but it's
not protected from things that could affect it, you know, so that
seems to be the idea. Okay, so now the גמרא says like
this, והא דאמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, veha de'amar Rav Yehuda amar
Shmuel, לא יעמוד אדם על גג זה ויקלוט מי גשמים מגגו של
חבירו. lo ya'amod adam al gag zeh ve'yiklot
mei geshamim mi'gago shel
chaveiro.
Do not, now this is this idea of רשויות חלוקות. reshuyot chalukot.
Okay, I have my apartment building, Michael has a connected apartment building,
we're right here, it's for שבת Shabbat purposes. Now, we're all contained,
anyway, on the top of a building and the building has walls,
so even without this, we're in a רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid. The
same way the building below is a רשות היחיד, reshut hayachid, the
roof on top is a רשות היחיד reshut hayachid because we imagine
that the walls continue upward, okay? So I can carry on my
rooftop, he can carry on his rooftop. But you know what I
can't do? Even though it's completely flat, if you're just looking at
the roof you would have no idea that below they're different buildings,
it just looks like one big roof, I cannot, well I can
go from, but I can't take something from one half of the
roof to this half of the roof because the same way, because
if we haven't made an עירוב, eiruv, an עירוב eiruv I don't
mean like strings, I mean, you know, we haven't gotten together with
some food, then these are, the same way I couldn't carry, as
if we had a window between our two things, we couldn't pass
something because there's different like ownerships and different domains, you can't carry
from one to the other without an עירוב. eiruv. So the same
way down here it's obvious that they're different, up here it looks
like one big roof, doesn't matter, you can't take something from one
half of the roof to the other half of the roof, okay?
So אדם מגג זה, adam mi'gag zeh, לא יעמוד אדם בגג זה
ויקלוט מי גשמים מגגו של חבירו. lo ya'amod adam bi'gag zeh ve'yiklot
mei geshamim mi'gago shel chaveiro.
Do not stand on one roof and, you know, sort of gather
or collect the rain from the other roof, okay? שכשם שדיורין חלוקין
מלמטה, she'keshem she'diyurin chalukin mi'lematah, I don't know why that's the scenario
but okay, because maybe rain is הפקר, hefker, so anyway, because the
same way that there are different inhabitants below, כך דיורין חלוקין מלמעלה,
kach diyurin chalukin mi'lemala, there are different inhabitants above, even though it
all looks like one flat rooftop, they're different רשויות. reshuyot. הני מילי,
Hani milei, now that הלכה halacha is לעניין שבת, l'inyan Shabbat, אבל
לעניין גט, aval l'inyan get, משום קפידא הוא וכולי האי לא קפדי
אינשי. mishum kpeida hu ve'chulei hai lo kapdi inshei. Different than what
we said before. Remember before we said that חד מקום מושלי אינשי,
chad makom moshli inshei, right? That you're only lending one space and
if you lent one half, if she was using this part of
the roof she wouldn't be using that, she wouldn't be able to
use that part of the roof. Here we're saying differently, we're saying,
look, the husband, you know, he doesn't mind which roof you use,
he wants you to get divorced, so he's letting you use a
space, so we don't define the other half of a roof as
a different space, and if the husband let her use it, it
would, she could even use the other half of the roof. He
says whatever space she's in, so he can basically use the other
half of the roof as well. Okay, yep.
Right, when it
says it's לעניין שבת, l'inyan Shabbat, no one's collecting rain
on שבת Shabbat anyway, right?
Right, so that's מוקצה muktzeh you mean. What? No, we פסקן pasken
that rain isn't מוקצה, muktzeh, so okay, okay, yeah. So if you
take a look, right, read Rashi, right? Because Rashi says בגיטין, be'Gittin,
היו לו שני גגים סמוכים זה לזה hayu lo shenei gagim s'muchim
zeh la'zeh והשאיל לה מקום בזה לקבל את גיטה, ve'hish'il lah makom
be'zeh l'kabel et gittah,
he said here you can use that rooftop of that building for
your גט, maybe Rashi makes a scenario even if he explicitly named
that one, וקבלתו בזה ve'kibalto be'zeh and she received the גט on
the other rooftop, לא אמרינן הכא רשויות חלוקות, lo amrinan hacha reshuyot
chalukot, we don't say like we had said earlier, we said earlier
that this, no, they're separate and he only... When you take one
space, דהא אמרינן לעיל תרי מקומות לא מושלי אינשי. de-ha amrinan l'eil
terei mekomot lo mushli inshi.
So because we said before, right, people doesn't lend you two spaces.
No, so that's משום קפידא הוא. mishum k'feida hu. So that's because
of being מקפיד. makpid. יש משאיל חצירו ומקפיד על ביתו. yesh mash'il
chatzeiro u-makpid al beito.
That if you lend the yard, you're not telling her she can
use the room. Okay? אבל כולי האי, aval kulei hai, but this
case, גגות סמוכים, gaggim smuchin,
it's all one big rooftop. ואין תשמישן קבוע וגס v'ein tashmishan kavua
v'gas and anyway people don't usually use rooftops so if I'm letting
you use the rooftop you can use both halves I don't care.
Okay. And so therefore לא קפדי אינשי. lo kapdi inshi. Yes?
If we switch examples here in the third case? Because first it
was owned by two people and now it's owned by one
person.
Yeah,
I was wondering about that, but you can't have a scenario where
he has rights to, you're right.
I mean, we're still in גיטין, right?
So yeah, I was wondering about that. You don't have the same
מציאות metziut of דיורין חלוקין diyurin chalukin of different spaces defined by
the fact that different people are living there because if he's the
one that's giving her permission to use it, right, then he has
to own both. I was wondering about that. Yes? I don't know
the answer to that. Okay.
Let's see. You have a question? Yeah? Alright, let's see. Okay. So
now it says like this: אמר אביי: Amar Abaye: שתי חצרות זו
לפנים מזו. shteichatzerot zu l'fanim mi-zo.
If you have two yards, one inside of the other. Could be
one behind the other, but it's easier to read it one inside
the other. Like again, like the sort of, you know,
concentric circles or
whatever, circumscribed square. Concentric, not co-cent. How would you describe that if
there's two squares inside of one? Anyway, one square contained in the
other. Okay. שתי חצרות זו לפנים מזו. shteichatzerot zu l'fanim mi-zo. פנימית
שלה וחיצונה שלו. pnimit shela v'chitzonah shelo. Okay. He owns the inner
yard and he owns the outer one. ומחיצות החיצונה עודפות על הפנימית.
u-mechitzot hachitzonah odfot al hapnimit. Like we said before, okay, as Jenna
said, she's in a fortress. Okay, but whatever it is, she basically,
okay, but this is not a building, okay? We've got like just
a yard. I own this yard, the woman owns this yard, right?
The guy owns that yard and he's got walls around or a
fence around to protect his yard and she's got like I don't
know a little picket fence or something like that. Whatever it might
be. Okay. That's the case. Now what happens?
וזרקו
לה. v'zarko lah. And he threw the get to her and
apparently you know where he was standing? He was standing out here.
And he threw the get to her and it's now over inside
the inside the walls of the outer one. Okay. So
where were we?
וזרקו לה. v'zarko lah. כיון שהגיע לאויר מחיצות החיצונה—wait keivan she-higia l'avir
mechitzot hachitzonah a
minute. וזרקו לה, כיון שהגיע לאויר מחיצות החיצונה
הרי זו מגורשת. v'zarko lah, keivan she-higia l'avir mechitzot hachitzonah harei zu
megureshet. Once it came to the air of the outer מחיצות, mechitzot,
she's divorced. מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? Why? פנימית גופה במחיצות החיצונה קמינטרא
pnimit gufah b'mechitzot hachitzonah kamintara because the inner one is in general
protected by the walls of the outer one. Now the question is
over which land is it, right? It could be in the air
space of the outer one but above her property. Okay. That would
make sense because now it's above her property, it's protected property by
his walls, but that's still considered protected inner property as a general
rule. Her property is implicitly protected by his walls. That makes sense.
To say that it would be over his yard and she would
be מגורשת megureshet. is very, very hard. So we're going to assume
it means that it's over her yard. Okay. Now מה שאין כן
בקופות, ma she-ein ken b'kupot, which would not be true if we're
talking about baskets. שתי קופות זו בתוך זו. shteikupot zu b'toch zu.
פנימית שלה וחיצונה שלו. pnimit shela v'chitzonah shelo. She has the inner
basket, he has the outer one and the outer one is a
bigger basket. וזרקו לה, v'zarko lah, and he threw it. In this
case, אפילו הגיע לאויר פנימית, afilu higia l'avir pnimit, even if, here's
her basket, right, and here's his basket, okay, and the get now
is even in the airspace of the inner one, not just the
airspace of the outer one, okay, even in that
case אינה מגורשת. megureshet? She's not. מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? Why? דהא
לא נח. de-ha lo nach. Because it didn't rest. Because this idea
that you have airspace, remember we had a question: do you have
airspace in ארבע אמות? But you certainly don't have a concept of
airspace by a basket, by כלים. keilim. You have an airspace by
yards, by property. You don't, your basket doesn't have airspace rights. Okay.
So when we say you can be קונה koneh something קנין כלי
kinyan kli and I throw an apple into your basket, okay, you
don't own that apple until it hits the bottom of your basket.
Your basket doesn't have airspace rights. Okay. So וכי נח מאי הוי?
v'chi nach mai havay? So now the
גמרא says, okay, but you're suggesting though that when it does come
to land in her basket, she is מגורשת. Why is she מגורשת?
כלי של לוקח ברשות מוכר הוא. kli shela b'lukiach b'reshut mocher hu.
It's her vessel in his domain because it's her vessel in his
vessel. So that's like her vessel is sitting in his domain.
It's like his yard, right?
Right, so the גמרא *Gemara* says: הכא במאי עסקינן בקופה שאין לה
שוליים *hacha be-mai askinan be-kuppa she-ein lah shulayim*.
No, the outer basket doesn't have a floor. So I don't know
exactly what the point is. I don't know what type of a
basket it is. I mean, no, it could be like that, you
know, it could be like it's got a—it's still connected, it's just
I don't know what you'd use it for. Anyway, the point is
that here the real חידוש *chiddush* is not that she's קונה *koneh*
when it falls, when it lands. We'll make a crazy scenario that
she'll קונה *koneh* when it lands because the outer one doesn't have
a floor. The real חידוש *chiddush* is that even when something is
in the air space of your basket, you're not קונה *koneh*, okay?
Forget his basket. Even when it's in the air space of your
basket, even if it was the only basket around, you're not קונה
*koneh* because baskets don't have air space. Yards have air space.
Baskets don't have air space. What if part of the basket were
sitting directly on the ground in his yard?
That also wouldn't work because then it would be also his רשות
*reshus*, right?
Okay, so by the time it gets into her basket it's already—yeah,
but there's—but it doesn't matter. If it's not in your yard, the
concept of guarded and air space, that's the exact point, is only
by land and property. Okay, but land in her
basket—if it lands in her basket, but her basket is sitting on
his yard, that does—or that's a question if that works, because that's
כלי שלוקח ברשות מוכרו *kli she-lokeach bi-reshut mochro*. That if it's my
basket, but it's in the person who is trying to give me
the object, if it's his yard, it's not clear it's really left
his space. It's in my space and it's in his space.
Does it become the space of the basket?
Okay, let's take a look.
You make a good point. A basket without a bottom is called
a fence.
Right. Well, I don't know. Anyway, I don't—that's not really—that wasn't—I know,
but that really wasn't the point. Okay, the point was there's no
concept of air space for baskets. Okay, we have two minutes and
we are going to read the next little משנה גמרא *Mishnah Gemara*
because it'll go fast. בית שמאי אומרים *Beis Shammai omrim*: פוטר אדם
את אשתו בגט ישן *poter adam et ishto be-get yashan*.
A person can divorce his wife with an old גט *get*. ובית
הלל אוסרים *u-Beis Hillel osrim*. And בית הלל *Beis Hillel* forbid it.
Now notice they don't say the גט *get* is פסול *pasul*, they
just forbid doing it, which allows the גמרא *Gemara* to ask what
will happen if they did do it. ואיזהו גט ישן *v-eizu get
yashan*? What is an old גט *get*? כל שנתייחד עמה מאחר שכתבו
לה *kol shenityached imah mei-achar she-ketavo lah*. It was written and not
given, and then they were in ייחוד *yichud*. So we're afraid, as
the גמרא *Gemara* is going to say, that they had sex after
it was written, she got pregnant, she'll have kids, she'll get divorced
with it two years from now, and people will look and they'll
say, "Oh, you had a kid before you
got—after you got your גט *get*," because they'll think the גט *get*
was given by the date it was written. במאי מיפלגי *be-mai miflagi*?
What's the debate? בית שמאי סברי *Beis Shammai savri*: לא אמרינן גזירה
שמא יאמרו גיטה קודם לבנה *lo amrinan gezeirah shema yomru gita kodem
livnah*. We're not concerned, we're not concerned that that scenario—we're not—even if
the scenario happened, we're not concerned that people will not understand, we
don't care about gossip. Anyway, the kid wouldn't be a ממזר *mamzer*,
it'd just be a kid born out of wedlock. We don't—go ahead,
give the גט *get*, we're not concerned about what people will say.
ובית הלל סברי *u-Beis Hillel savri*: no, אמרינן גזירה שמא יאמרו גיטה
קודם לבנה *amrinan gezeirah shema yomru gita kodem livnah*. We're afraid that
the גט *get* will be given, it'll—afterwards it'll have an earlier date,
she'll be pregnant, people will say she got pregnant after she was
divorced. אמר רבי אבא אמר שמואל *Amar Rabbi Abba amar Shmuel*: Now,
because even בית הלל *Beis Hillel* just said you don't do it,
אוסרים *osrim*, and they didn't say it's פסול *pasul*, we're going to
ask the following case: בדיעבד *bedieved*. So אמר רבי אבא אמר שמואל
*Amar Rabbi Abba amar Shmuel*: אם נישאת לא תצא *im niseit lo
tetzei*. If she used it, this גט *get*, he was given it,
and she got married, she does not have to get divorced. בדיעבד
*bedieved* the גט *get* is כשר *kasher*. ואיכא דאמרי *v-ika de-amri* אמר
רבי אבא אמר שמואל *Amar Rabbi Abba amar Shmuel*: not only that,
אם נתגרשה *im nitgarsha*, before that she got married, the guy gave
it. Once she gave it,
תינשא לכתחילה *tinasei l'chatchilah*, she can get married לכתחילה *l'chatchilah*. The הלכה
*halacha* is just you're not supposed to give it, okay, but if
it was given, she's completely divorced, even לכתחילה *l'chatchilah* she can go
ahead and get married.